Guide to the Mike Topp Papers MSS.188
Fales Library and Special Collections
Mike Topp Papers
1949-2008
1980-2006
Fales Library and Special Collections
Topp, Mike
MSS.188
6.5 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons and one manuscript box
1 electronic discs (cd-rom)
Mike Topp is a poet, editor, and member of The Unbearables, a loosely organized group of Downtown writers and artists, known for protests against notions of "good" or "bad" literature and art. This collection consists of Topp's poem drafts and idea notes, plus published works he contributed to and edited.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged at the series level in three series: Series I: Notes, ideas, unpublished writing, web content; Series II: Printed published works and anthologies; Series III: Correspondence, photos, and ephemera.
Biographical Note
A poet and editor, Mike Topp is a member of The Unbearables, a loosely organized group of Downtown writers and artists, known for protests against notions of "good" or "bad" literature and art. He has worked closely with Ron Kolm and Sparrow, two other Unbearables. Online sources state that Topp was born in Washington, D.C., and currently lives in New York City "unless he has died or moved". He received a master's degree in English from New York University in 1983. Recent Topp books include Sasquatch Stories and 29 Mini-Essays.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
New York University purchased the collection from Mike Topp in 2005.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact Fales Library with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The Mike Topp Papers consist of notes, writings, published poems, anthologies, and correspondence related to Topp's work. Materials document his creative process and professional relationships with other artists, publishers, and poetry organizations. Subjects covered include the Unbearables, poetry, creative writing, downtown artists, and sexuality. Document types include correspondence (handwritten notes and printed emails), photographs (printed and on CD-R), letterpress chapbooks, and ephemeral items, plus some original artwork.
Related Materials
For more information about the Unbearables, see the Ron Kolm Papers (MSS 079) and the Sparrow Papers (MSS 096) in the Fales Library and Special Collections.
American poetry -- 20th century.; Unbearables (Literary group); chapbooks; Kolm, Ron; Sparrow, (American poet)
- Series I: Notes, Ideas, Unpublished Writing, Web Content
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains Topp's notes and ideas, poem drafts, manuscripts, and reviews. Also included are some works by other writers and artists.
  - Notebooks, diaries, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
  - Writings, poems, notes, drafts, 1982-2004 (Box 1, Folder 10-19)
  - Realpoetik, Gargoyle, Timothy McSweeney, Exquisite Corpse, 1997-2005 (Box 1, Folder 20-30)
  - Happy Ending, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Miranda July, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - My Weekend in Germany, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Writings, poems, notes, drafts, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Outlaw Bible of American Poetry, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Own Your Own, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Galerie St. Etienne, Self-Taught Artists, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Greatest Hits, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Really Small Talk, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Really Small Talk, Monkey Bicycle, Stuyvesant Bee, 2004-2008 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Partial Bibliography, Public Illumination Magazine; List of published works, 1982-2008 (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
  - David Trinidad Magazine; This is Stupid, I Love You, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Fromage to Eternity, Fastest Gun in the West, Five Stories, undated (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
  - Little Fish, undated (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
  - Return of the Dead Mother with New Problems; Tropicana, undated (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Writings, poems, notes, drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 27-36)
- Series II: Printed Published Works and Anthologies
  Series II contains poetry anthologies, newsletters, zines, and letterpress books Topp contributed to or edited.
  - Letterpress Chapbooks, Zines, Newsletters, Exhibitions, 1980-2004 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - American Book Review, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Angry Dog Midget Editions, 2001-2003 (Box 6)
  - Appearances, 1994-1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - beet, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Between C and D, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
  - Bookforum, Artforum, 1996-2002 (Box 7)
  - Brooklyn Review, 1989-1998 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Canary River Review, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - The Curse, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Evergreen Review Reader, 1979-1993 (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
  - Exquisite Corpse, 1986-1997 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - House Organ, 1997-2000 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Lit, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - LIz * Val, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Long Shot, 1994-2001 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lungfull!, 1996-2005 (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
  - Mudfish, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - New Observations, 1989-1995 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - New York Press, 1992-1997 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
  - Paris Review, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Pink Pages, 1992-1998 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - The Poetry Project, 1988-2005 (Box 4, Folder 16-18, Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Public Illumination Magazine, 1981-2001 (Box 6)
  - Qualiteria, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Quarterly, 1993-1995 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Red Tape, 1984, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Secret Agent Nick America, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sirowitz, Hal, Chapbooks, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Styles, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Talisman, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Toilet Paper, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Unbearable Smoot, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Unbearables, 1988-2001 (Box 5, Folder 12-15)
  - L'Uomo Vogue Sport, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Whirl, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Publications: Brooklyn Review, Downtown, The Observatory, 1988-2002 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Series III: Correspondence, Photos, Ephemera
  Series III contains correspondence (handwritten notes and printed emails), photographs (printed and on CD-R), and ephemeral items, plus some original artwork. Correspondents include Sparrow, Joe Brainard, Iggy Pop, John Cage, William Wegman, and Gillian McCain.
  - Correspondence, 1985-2006 (Box 6, Folder 1-15)
  - E. Village lease, photos, passport, 1982-1999 (Box 6, Folder 16-18, Box Shared Fales 015)
  - Calendars, 1998-2006 (Box 6, Folder 19-21)
  - Original Art, 1973-2003 (Box 6, Folder 22-25)
  - Ephemera: Comic books, buttons, commemorative stamps, baseball scorecard, paperback, art opening cards, Franklin Furnace poster, sunglasses, 1948-2005 (Box 6, Folder 26-30)